<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A defence of King Charles I occasion'd by the lyes and scandals of many bad men of this age / by Richard Hollingworth ...</title>
            <author>Hollingworth, Richard, 1639?-1701.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44223</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2502</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13622</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12539845</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12539845</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62943</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44223)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62943)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 670:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A defence of King Charles I occasion'd by the lyes and scandals of many bad men of this age / by Richard Hollingworth ...</title>
                  <author>Hollingworth, Richard, 1639?-1701.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Eddowes ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62943:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62943:1"/>
            <p>A DEFENCE OF King Charles I. Occaſion'd by the LYES &amp; SCANDALS OF Many BAD MEN of this AGE.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Richard Hollingworth,</hi> D. D. Their Majeſties Chaplain, at St. <hi>Botolph Aldgate, London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Eddowes,</hi> under the Piazza of the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:62943:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62943:2"/>
            <head>TO THE KING &amp; QUEENS Moſt Excellent Majeſties.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe Your Majeſties,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Subject of this Diſcourſe being no leſs a Perſon than King <hi>Charles</hi> I. of Bleſſed Memory, and Your Royal Grandfather, whoſe Throne You ſo happily fill, and whoſe Virtues and Graces You daily imitate; I therefore thought the Dedication of it proper for none but Crowned Heads, upon which ſcore I humbly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, ſuch as it is, to lay it at Your Sacred Feet, hoping that it may be ſerviceable to ſupport the Honour and Reputation of Monarchy in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, (which, I am certain, is ſtruck at through the Sides of this Great Prince) to preſerve the Peace and Happineſs of Your Majeſties Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to ſecure Your Majeſties from the Danger, as well of flattering and pretending Friends, as of publick and open Enemies: Which good effect that it may have, ſhall be the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Majeſties moſt humble and dutiful Subject and Servant, <hi>Ric. Hollingworth.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:62943:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF thoſe, who have of late made it their Buſineſs to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, will, after this, repent and do ſo no more, then I promiſe, this Diſcourſe, as it is my firſt, ſo it ſhall be the laſt I will put forth of this nature. But if they are reſolved againſt Conviction, and will act againſt Noon-day-light, and will continue to load this Great and Good man's Memory ſtill with their wonted Calumnies and Reproaches; I do here tell them, that I have ſo much more to ſay in his behalf, which I could not crowd into theſe Papers, (becauſe I was willing it ſhould be <hi>every man's Money</hi>) that, if it be poſſible, will put them to a ſhame. And I do here aſſure them, if they will not ſuffer Modeſty and Good-manners to command them for the time to come, they ſhall have it; for, I am reſolved, as long as I can hold a Pen in my Hand, I will not drop this Cauſe, namely, <hi>The Defence of</hi> Charles <hi>the Firſt.</hi> I have but one thing more, and that is, That I cannot believe that man loves me, let his Profeſſions be never ſo great and many, nay, but that he has a Spight to and Deſign againſt me, who in all Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies and Places, without Cauſe or Provocation, calls my Grandfather Knave and Raſcal.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farwel.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62943:3"/>
            <head>A DEFENCE OF King CHARLES the Firſt, &amp;</head>
            <p>KING <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt was a perſon whoſe Life I have diligently look'd into, and as ſeriouſly conſidered, and in doing both, have found my ſelf equally affected with Joy and Grief; with Joy, to meet with a perſon, under ſo great and many Temptations as Princes muſt needs be, ſo admirably tempered, ſo greatly conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending, ſo ready to comply with whatever was preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him for the Good of his Subjects, of ſo great Patience under the greateſt Sufferings and the moſt hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Indignities put upon him, of ſo great Conſtancy to the Religious Perſwaſions of his own Mind, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the enjoyment of his Crown, nor yet his Life, could bribe him to forſake them.</p>
            <p>Further, to meet with a Prince of ſo affable a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, and that attended with ſuch pithy and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Diſcourſes, as made ſome of thoſe who were his Keepers at <hi>Holdenly-Houſe,</hi> not only love, but admire him ever after; ſo that they not only wiſhed, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62943:4"/>to put him in a better condition. Laſtly, A Prince of ſo ſolid a Judgment, as all his Writings and Diſputes do teſtifie, and alſo ſo ſerious and awful, as well as conſtant in his Devotions; I ſay, when I meet with theſe true Accounts in Hiſtory, I cannot forbear prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing God with the greateſt joy, that there was ſuch a perſon of his Degree, and in his High ſtation, that was born into, and lived in the World to be a Pattern to future Princes, as well as to all other ſort of Perſons, of true Virtue and real Goodneſs.</p>
            <p>But, on the other hand, I have been often overwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, as it were, with Sorrow and a loading Grief, to find this Prince, ſo every ways Great and Good, ſo rudely handled, ſo barbarouſly uſed, ſo ignobly and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generouſly refuſed not only the Liberty of his Body, but the free exerciſe of his Religion in that way which he had ſo often and alſo ſo ſolemnly declared to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the juſt and well-made ſatisfaction of his Mind and Judgment; to find him libell'd by every petty and ſawcy Scribler, and thoſe Libels countenanc'd, and alſo ſpread abroad by a Factious number of Men, who deſigned nothing, but by his Ruine to raiſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into Places of Wealth and Power. I ſay, when I meet with theſe, and a thouſand more Affronts put upon him, enough to have broke any Heart but his, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but entertain my ſelf with ſorrowful Thoughts, nor yet forbear ſuch Reſentments as almoſt force me to break out into undecent Paſſions and violent Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon thoſe men, who once ſwore Allegiance to him, and afterwards, forgetting all their Obligations, trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him as one of their Slaves or Footboys. But however, it would be ſome allay to a man's Grief, if he could find the preſent Generation of this Kingdom, eſpecially many of thoſe whoſe Anceſtors had too great an hand in theſe vile and ſcornful Treatments of this Great and Excellent
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:62943:4"/>Perſon, to make an atonement for the Faults of their Progenitors, by bewailing of them, and by a conſtant forwardneſs to give this Good man that juſt and true Character that his Worth and Merits do call for at all honeſt and conſidering mens hands: But, alas! when I find at this time of the day, inſtead of this, theſe very men, who ſucceed in Principles thoſe who impriſoned and at laſt murdered him; I ſay, when I find ſo great numbers of them vindicating his Death, and in order to that, loading his Memory with all the filthy Accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and groundleſs, as well as falſe, Aſperſions, that Wit and Malice put together, can amaſſe and heap up, never ſpeaking of him, but as a Tyrant, a Rogue, a Raſcal, nay, and a Papiſt too, though he ſo ſtrenuouſly aſſerted and pleaded the Proteſtant Cauſe, as it is profeſſed by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and calling the day on which he was murthered, and which is appointed by the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Power of the Nation to be religiouſly obſerved, <hi>The Madding Day,</hi> as it is in a late lewd Pamphlet, that goes under the name of <hi>Ludlow:</hi> Why, I muſt needs ſay, this ſwells my Grief above its uſual Bank, as well as ſtirs and raiſes my juſt Indignation againſt ſuch a vile Brood, who, under pretence of Duty, and entire Affections to Their preſent Majeſties, (believe them who will or can) are daily abuſing him from whoſe Loins they came, and whoſe Virtues they daily imitate.</p>
            <p>And therefore, from theſe two Paſſions of Grief and Anger, thus juſtly grounded, I am reſolved, in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Treatiſe, to vindicate this great Prince, and if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, to ſhame his implacable Enemies, who do ſhew by what they ſo frequently vent, that they have nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Knowledge, Wiſdom, nor Good-Manners, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed any thing elſe that belongs to the Human as well as Chriſtian Nature; the influency of either of which, if ſuffer'd, would make them tender of the Reputation and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62943:5"/>Memory of one, whoſe Virtues and Graces were as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous as were the Perfidiouſneſs and Treachery, the Hypocriſie and Perjury of thoſe who imbrewed their Hands in his Sacred Blood.</p>
            <p>And here I muſt tell the Reader, that I intend only to run through the laſt Eight years of his Reign; for tho' there might be ſome miſtakes in his Government before, (as, What Government is without them?) yet now he offers to redreſs all, and did ſo as far as he could be ſatisfied things were out of order; and, I am certain, from the beginning of the Long Parliament, <hi>November</hi> the 4th. to the day of his death, <hi>January</hi> 48. that he did every thing almoſt that deſerved a better reception than it met withal, and made ſuch various Offers and Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcentions, as would have pleaſed any ſort of men, but thoſe who were reſolved to be Maſters of his whole Crown and Dignity, together with his Revenues, and the Eſtates of all thoſe who from Principles of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ſtood by and aſſerted his juſt and righteous Cauſe. And in this Undertaking I promiſe the Reader to be true and impartial, and to offer nothing but what I have a good and truly-acknowledg'd Authority for; for I ſcorn to ſet Pen to Paper, with a diſign to cheat and impoſe upon the World, which when I have done, I fear not the Reflections of any prejudic'd, reſolv'd, and unreaſonable men whatſoever.</p>
            <p>When the Parliament ſate down in 40. it is plain to any man that reads the Hiſtory with a clear and equal mind, That the King purpoſed and reſolved to conſent to every thing they could offer him, which might be really for the Good of his Kingdom; and that if any Grievance was left unredreſſed, it ſhould not be his, but their own fault, only ſuppoſing they would not make Grievances where there were none, and overturn the Government inſtead of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62943:5"/>healing the Sores thereof. And therefore, in his firſt Speech, he tells them frankly, That he was reſolv'd to put himſelf freely and clearly on the Love and Affection of his <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subjects; and withal, promiſes them at the ſame time to concurr with them ſo heartily, that all the World may ſee, that his Intentions have ever been, and ſhall be, to make this a glorious and flouriſhing King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. And, I think, he that reads the firſt half-years Tranſactions betwixt him and this Parliament, will find he made his word good to a tittle; for whatſoever they offered to him by way of Bill, which the Nation groan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under before, as a real, nay, but as a fancied Burthen, he preſently paſſes it. As for inſtance; The <hi>Star-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> had been long complained of as a Grievance, and therefore he ſigns the Bill to take it away. Further, the <hi>High-Commiſſion</hi> was a Court that moſt mens Mouths were opened againſt, tho' it was well deſigned, when in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> days it was firſt erected; and he conſents to take that away too. The <hi>Ship-Money,</hi> tho' great and very learned Lawyers had given their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, That the exacting of it in ſome caſes was accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Law; yet he reſolving to ſet all right at once, betwixt himſelf and many of his diſcontented People, he gives that up alſo, and withal, conſents, that the late Proceedings touching <hi>Ship-Money</hi> ſhould be declared void. And, to pleaſe the <hi>Weſtern.</hi> Gentlemen, and many others of inferiour rank, he paſſes an Act againſt the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachments and Oppreſſions of the <hi>Stannery Courts.</hi> And, to pleaſe others throughout the Nation, as well as them, he ſigns another Bill, relating to the Metes and Bounds of the Forreſt; and all theſe things done in a very ſhort time. And after this, to let his People ſee, that all Dangers from Bad mens wicked Counſels, for the time to come, ſhould be prevented, he ſigns a Bill for a Triennial Parliament, wherein, upon a Neglect at
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62943:6"/>Court, or from the better ſort of men in the Country, to ſummon a Choice, he puts it into the power of the very. Conſtables to do it; namely, to meet and chufe Repreſentives: Which, certainly; was as great a Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcention as was ever made by a Prince, and would have ſatisfied any but thoſe who were reſolved to carry a Game further than was at that time ſeen by men of clean and undeſigning Minds.</p>
            <p>And after this, when they thought things would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be well, until all ſorts of Subjects were converſant in nothing elſe, but what was proper for their Calling, and therefore fancied, that if the Biſhops were removed out of the Houſe of Lords, they would have more lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to attend their Spiritual Empl<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ments; why even this Bill, together with that which offered violence to the Peace and Quiet of his Mind all the days of his Life, namely, the Bill for attainding the great Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> he orders by Commiſſioners to be pa<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ſed. And, what can any man think, after this, could give occaſion for Diſcontent or finding Fault. If any thing could per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade men, that the King was reſolved nor to break with his People, but to lay a firm Foundation of Duty on their ſides for the time to come, certainly a man would think this would do; though, God knows, by the ſequel we find it did not, but the more he gave, the bolder they grew in their Requeſts, or rather in their Demands; and therefore, the next thing they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented him withal, which was a thing, I verily believe, never a Prince that had ſate upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Throne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, would have granted; Granted did I ſay? nay, would ſcornfully have rejected: Yet to ſhew he was reſolved to honour them with an entire Confidence, he paſſes that too, and with it not only all the future Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, of his Life, but his Life too, and that was the Bill for the Parliament to ſit during their pleaſure: Such
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62943:6"/>an Act of Kindneſs, as one would have thought, ſhould have obliged them for ever, and ſhut the door againſt all Suſpicions of him. Great and Good man hadſt thou had any jealouſie of this People's Kindneſs and Duty to thee, thou wouldſt have ſuffered thy Hand rather to have withered off, than by it to have ſigned a Bill where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thou loſeſt almoſt all thy Power at one blow.</p>
            <p>And now ſurely all Clouds are blown away, and the Sky looks clear, and there is a mutual Harmony, and an undiſturbed Intercourſe betwixt him and his People, eſpecially conſidering that he is ſo far from repenting of what he has done, that he is ſtill continuing to invite them, both by Speeches and Meſſages, to propoſe any thing to him that might make them both happy, (provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded they did not invade the Eſſentials of an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, and ſtrip him of every thing but the Name of a King) with all manner of aſſurance, that he would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with them; as any man may ſatisfie himſelf, that converſes with the Hiſtory and Tranſactions of thoſe times.</p>
            <p>But, alas, all theſe Condeſcentions would not do; and tho' he, good man, flatter'd himſelf with an eaſie Belief, that he had done what was fitting for a gracious King to do, in order to ſtill the voice of further Complaints, yet for all that, when for neceſſary reaſons he took a Journey to <hi>Scotland,</hi> theſe men, whoſe Requeſts he had thus largely anſwered, in his abſence to ſhew their gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude for what was done before, appoint a Committee, who being pick'd and choſen men, drew up a Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance, wherein they made the moſt bitter Reflections upon his former Government, and expoſed him to the cenſure and ill thoughts of his leſs-diſcerning Subjects, and which was ſo very unmannerly, as well as falſe, that when it came to be delated in the whole Houſe, after ſitting up all night, and thereby wearying many of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62943:7"/>ancient Gentlemen, and being proteſted-againſt by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny learned and worthy Patriots in the Houſe, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried only by eleven Votes, yet it was ordered to be printed, on purpoſe to enflame the Nation againſt him. Notwithſtanding which affront to his Perſon and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, (after he had fairly anſwered it, and vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelf from thoſe horrid Aſperſions wherewith they had loaded him, fairly proving, that the preſent Miſeries and future Dangers of the Nation lay at their door, and not at his.) I ſay, notwithſtanding this, he continues ſtill to ſollicite them, by Meſſage after Meſſage, to offer any thing to him wherein the true Intereſt of the Kingdom was concerned, and he would be ready to gratifie them, by giving it the Royal <hi>Fiat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And when through Tumults and too-much-counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanc'd Riots he withdrew from <hi>Whitehall,</hi> being under apprehenſion of Affronts deſign'd to be offered to his Perſon, if not ſomething worſe, yet he ceaſes not to call upon them, to conſider the Nations Good, and the ſettling it upon ſuch Foundations as neither the Monarch might invade the juſt Rights of the People, nor the People encroach upon the Rights of his Crown and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: And ſo he tells them upon their preſenting their Petition at <hi>Theobalds,</hi> and afterwards at <hi>New-market,</hi> in the ſame month, when after hearing their Declaration read, he expoſtulated in theſe words: <hi>What would you have? Have I violated your Laws? Have I denied to paſs any one Bill for the Eaſe and Security of my Subjects? God ſo deal with me and mine, as all my Thoughts and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions are upright, for the maintenance of the true Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Profeſſion, and for the Obſervation and Preſervation of the Laws of this Land.</hi> Expreſſions ſurely that do not in the leaſt ſavour of that Tyranny and Oppreſſion with which, at this time, by many wicked perſons, his <hi>Memory</hi> is charged. 'Tis true, theſe Applications from
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62943:7"/>the two Houſes, at this time, were for nothing leſs than the Militia; but, Can any man accuſe him for a Tyrant, becauſe he would not part with that which his Anceſtors alwaies enjoy'd, and without which a King is indeed but the ſhadow of a King; eſpecially not to part with it at that time, when ſo little a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard had been paid to his Perſon, nay, ſo many Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities had not only been promoted but encouraged too by thoſe very men, whom nothing now could ſatisfie, but the whole Power of the Sword?</p>
            <p>Well, the King continuing ſtedfaſt to his Reſolutions, and deaf to all their Importunities, telling them, he would not part with his Militia for an hour; which any wiſe man, that conſidered the preſent poſture of Affairs, would judge he had great reaſon to do, the Parliament falls into great Paſſions and Reſentments, and reſolve to be as ſtiff on the other ſide, and not to abate him an Ace of their Demands; and ſo intent are they upon this very thing, that though the King ſent to them to digeſt into one body all the Grievances of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and to ſend them to him, promiſing his favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Aſſent to thoſe Means which ſhould be found moſt effectual for Redreſs, wherein, as he ſays, he would not only equal, but exceed the moſt Indulgent Prince; (words which do not uſe to drop from the Mouth of a Tyrant, as he is falſly called by ſome at this day.) Yet all this was nothing, the Militia they muſt have, or the Nation is undone, and rather than fail, they will take it into their Hands by force: And ſo they did, after they had ſent the King a downright Meſſage, That if his Majeſty did not agree with the two Houſes, to ſettle the Militia, that then, for his and the Kingdoms ſafety, they ſhall be conſtrained of themſelves, without His Majeſty, to ſettle the neceſſary buſineſs of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia. And they were as good as their words; ſeize it
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62943:8"/>they did, in ſpight of all the King could ſay or proclaim to the contrary.</p>
            <p>But, before the War actually broke out, the King was gone to <hi>York,</hi> and made it the place of his Royal Reſidence, hoping thereby to cool the Heats that were at <hi>London,</hi> and in ſome little time to be invited thither, to live with more Honour and Safety than he did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Now, while the King ſtaid at <hi>York,</hi> what Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations he made to the Gentlemen and Citizens of that that County and City, what Aſſurances he gave them of his Reſolutions to govern by Law, and no otherwiſe, and of his protecting and countenancing the Proteſtant Religion, may be eaſily known by any man, who will but look over the faithful Hiſtorians of thoſe Times.</p>
            <p>The ſame Aſſurances he gave to the Inhabitants of <hi>Lincoln-ſhire</hi> and <hi>Leiceſter-ſhire;</hi> and when he was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to raiſe an Army, which was after the Parliament had voted the Neceſſity of a War with him, and after they had ſeized his Militia as far as they could; why, to let the World then ſee what he aimed at, he does aſſure the Gentlemen, whoſe Loyalty engaged them early on his ſide, <hi>Sept.</hi> 19.42. and does promiſe them in the preſence of Almighty God, and as he hopes for his Bleſſing and Protection, that he would, to the utmoſt of his Power, defend and maintain the true Proteſtant Religion eſtabliſh'd in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and, by the Grace of God, in the ſame he would live and dye. The Truth is, to repeat all that he ſaid of this nature, in ſeveral Counties, and to ſeveral Parties, would be end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and not at all ſuit with my diſigned Brevity.</p>
            <p>And now we come to another Scene of Action, and, God knows, a very melancholly one: For, through the High and Imperious Demands of the Parliament, to which the King could no ways, without ſtripping him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of every thing but the Name of a <hi>King,</hi> the Sword,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62943:8"/>the Unhappy Sword is drawn, and the poor Kingdom inſtead of being an Iſland of Peace and Plenty, is made a Field of Blood, and the Father appears againſt the Son, and the Son againſt the Father; our Plough-ſhares are turned into Spears, and our Pruning-hooks into Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Hoſtility: And methinks it ſhould grieve both King and Parliament, the one to ſee and hear of the Deſtruction of his own Children, as I may juſtly call them, and the other to hear ſo frequent Tidings, not only of the loſs of their Fellow-Subjects Lives, but alſo of the ruine of their Lands and Houſes. Do not they both ſtrive which ſhould moſt court each other to Peace? And do not they abate of their former De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, as well as ſtiff Adherencies? Methinks the Cries and Loſſes of the poor innocent Inhabitants of the Kingdom ſhould pierce their Ears, and melt their Hearts, and make them forget all their former Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Reſentments. Why truly, to give the two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes their due, they did at this time ſend Propoſals, as if they had been truly aſſected with the Nations Miſeries; but, in the mean time, (I am ſorry I can ſay no otherwife) they were ſuch Propoſals as they could, upon all reaſonable and fair Conſiderations and Debates with themſelves, expect no good Succeſs of, becauſe they could not but know be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-hand they would be denied, inſomuch, as the King had told them again and again, where he would ſtop, and how far he would go, eſpecially as to <hi>Church-Affairs.</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſs in theſe Propoſals would ſatisfie them, than the aboliſhing, by Act of Parliament, the whole Hierarchy, to which he was ſworn by his Coronation-Oath, ſettling the Militia as they pleaſed themſelves, the King's diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banding his Army (made up of the beſt Nobility and Gentry of the Kingdom) and withal, which was a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Aſſront to Majeſty than could be ſuppoſed to them, in coming to demand the five Members: He muſt be
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62943:9"/>obliged as it were, and in effect, to beg thoſe <hi>Members</hi> Pardon for wronging them, with what he thought and could by good Evidence prove Matter of Truth; Which certainly was but to <hi>ſeem</hi> to deſire Peace, and at the ſame time to reſolve to continue the War.</p>
            <p>But now the next thing to be conſidered is, after theſe Propoſals, how the King manages himſelf, and what ſteps he makes towards a Peace; and truly, I think, according to my poor Judgment, he now acts according to what he alwaies pretended and ſolemnly avowed, to wit, as a true Father of his Country; for he propoſes, That his Revenue, Magazines, Towns, Ships, and Forts, may be reſtored to him; that what hath been done contrary to Law and his Right, may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called; and that he will conſent to the execution of all Laws concerning Popery or Reformation: Nay, he fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tells them, That he had given up all the Faculties of his Soul to an earneſt endeavonr of a Peace and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation with his Subjects. So that to me hitherto the Fault lies not at His Majeſty's door, ſay the Enemies to his Memory what they pleaſe; for, let them but abate of the rigour of their Demands, and not ask him things wholly inconſiſtent with his Honour and Conſcience, with his Crown and Dignity, and the iſſue of Blood is ſtopped preſently, and the Nation reſtored to its former ſtate of Peace; for ſtill he ſtands ready, and proſſers again and again, to ſign any Bill that, in his own, and the Judgment of many Wiſe and Good men about him, who were true lovers of their Countrys Licerties and Properties, was neceſſary for making the Nation more happy in its Privileges than it had been in all Ages be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. And truly, it ſo, I ſee no Cauſe for continuing a Deſtructive War in the Bowels of the Kingdom, nor for ſtanding upon their Points at that rigid rate they did, eſpecially when ſo many of their Brethren and fellow-Members
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62943:9"/>of both Houſes, upon great diſſatisſaction at their Proceedings had left their ſtation, and took in, out of Principles of Loyalty and Duty, with their Maſter's Cauſe, venturing both their Lives, Families, and Eſtates upon it, which no man can believe wiſe men would have done, if they had not ſeen great Reaſon to queſtion the Integrity of the prevailing part of the Parliament: So that hitherto there appears no juſt Reaſon for thoſe many ſcandalous Reflections, that in Coffee-houſes and other places of publick Intercourſe or private Communication, are made upon this great and excellent man. And thus ended the year 42, all the King's Propoſals and Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcentions being neglected and ſlighted.</p>
            <p>The year 43. begins with a Treaty for Peace, at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> Commiſſioners for the Parliament being, the Lord <hi>Northumberland,</hi> the Lord <hi>Wenmain,</hi> Mr. <hi>Peirepoint,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hollis, &amp;c.</hi> who were civilly treated, both by the King himſelf and many of his great Officers; which Treaty was managed not by Commiſſioners on the King's ſide, but by himſelf.</p>
            <p>And truly, he that reads it over, muſt needs confeſs, that His Majeſty deſerved the Commendation Mr. <hi>Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock,</hi> who was one of them, in his <hi>Memorials</hi> gives of him, to wit, That in this Treaty the King manifeſted his great Parts and Ability, ſtrength of Reaſon, and quickneſs of Apprehenſion, with much patience in hearing what was objected againſt him, wherein he allowed all Freedom, and would himſelf ſum up the Arguments, and give a moſt clear Judgment upon them. This is Mr. <hi>Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock</hi>'s Character. And, to let all the World ſee his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs to do every thing which might reaſonably anſwer the Kingdoms Expectation, and make it happy, he tells theſe Commiſſioners, That he hath nor denied any one thing, propoſed to him by both Houſes, which in Juſtice could be required of him, or in reaſon expected: And
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62943:10"/>the Truth of it is, had not their Demands been ſo very high in this, as well as in other Treaties, (which, a man muſt think, were made on purpoſe, by the prevalence of a deſigning ſelf-intereſted Party, to continue the War) I am certain Peace had enſued upon this Treaty; for, the King ſtill, like a tender Father, groaned under the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of his Honour and Conſcience were not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, in order to put an end to that deſolating War: And therefore, that this Treaty had no better effect, was not the King's fault, but of thoſe that bound up their Commiſſioners to ſuch narrow limits, that His Majeſty, without doing Injuſtice to the Eſſentials of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality, could not comply with the Propoſals that were offered: And this he complains of himſelf, That they bound up their Committee in that manner, as to Time and Power, as might wholly render it ineffectual.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, after the Commiſſioners returned home, the Lords and Commons put out a Declaration upon the Proceedings of this Treaty, which I ſhall no ways re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon, but only tell the World, the King preſently put out an Anſwer to it, which whoſoever will be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to read, will find His Majeſty the ſame perſon ſtill, a man of true Honour and Conſcience, and ready to ſerve all the Needs and Conveniencies of his Country, and no ways deſerving thoſe Reflections which were made by his Subjects at that time, to render him odious to his People; and I do deſire the preſent Maligners of this Great Perſon to read over his Declaration in anſwer to the Parliaments, and then tell me whether he deſigned any Tyrannical and Arbitrary Power, and was guilty of the Stubborneſs that he is falſly accuſed of by Deſigners againſt Monarchy at this time: for, hearing nothing for a Month together, by way of Meſſage, after he had par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Commiſſioners, he, Good man, in order
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62943:10"/>to a Compliance, ſends another Meſſage to them, and in it requires, as they will anſwer to God, to him, and all the World, that they will not longer ſuffer their fellow-Subjects to welter in each others Blood; that they will remember by whoſe Authority, and to what end they met in that Council, and ſend ſuch an Anſwer to His Majeſty, as may open a Door, to let in a firm Peace and Security to the whole Kingdom. And after this, that, if poſſible, a ſtop might be put to this Bloodſhed in the Bowels of his Kingdom, he ſends another Meſſage for another Treaty, wherein he promiſes them, after he had expreſſed a becoming Pity for the Miſeries of the Nation, that no Endeavours or Concurrence of his ſhall be wanting; and that he might give infallible Proof, that thoſe Deſires of his were not feigned and pretended, but real and hearty, after his defeat of <hi>Waller</hi> at <hi>Croptedy-Bridge,</hi> he even then, by a Meſſage, courts the Lords and Commons to a Peace, and tells them in theſe words; That from an earneſt and conſtant endeavouring of Peace, as no diſcouragement given him on the contrary Party ſhall make him ceaſe, ſo no Succeſs on his ſhall ever divert him. Words ſpoke like a man of true Bowels and Affection to his People. And after this, from <hi>Traveſtock,</hi> when he had defeated the Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi> in <hi>Cornwal,</hi> and made ſo advantagious a Conqueſt, yet ſo far is he from being puffed up with that Succeſs, ſo far from ſhewing any inclination to enlarge his Power, above what was for his Subjects good, that he even then, in the midſt of his Laurels and Triumphs, ſends to the two Houſes, and tells them. It having pleaſed God in ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent a manner to bleſs his Arms in thoſe parts with Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, yet he did not ſo much joy in the Bleſſing for any other Conſideration, as for the hopes he had, that it might be a means to make others lay to Heart, as he did, the Miſeries brought and continued upon the Kingdom by
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62943:11"/>this unnatural War, and that it may open their Ears, and diſpoſe their Minds to embrace Offers of Peace and Reconciliation. Which Meſſage, after ſo great a Succeſs, certainly argued not the Spirit of a Tyrant, as our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Common-wealths-men call him, but the Compaſſion of a tender Father, whoſe Bowels yearned for the Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries his Kingdom laboured under, eſpecially if we add what he a little after ſaid in a publick Proclamation, where, after he had complained of receiving no Anſwer to the two former importunate Meſſages, he tells the World he deſired a Treaty for Peace, in which he does aſſure all his People, upon his Royal Word, and the Faith of a Chriſtian, which was the greateſt Security he could give them, that he would inſiſt only upon the Settling and Continuation of the true Reformed Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, his own undoubted Rights, the Privileges of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and his Subjects Liberties and Properties, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the known Laws of the Land. And what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this was truly neceſſary for the Peoples Happineſs truly I cannot divine.</p>
            <p>And thus far things went, and theſe Condeſcentions the King made, when his Affairs were very proſperous, and the Scale ſeemed to be turned on his ſide, which, I think, was an Argument of Sincerity on his ſide; and will take off all Objections made againſt his future Offerings for Peace; as if bare Neceſſity drove him, when Succeſs fell upon the Parliaments Forces.</p>
            <p>The two Houſes therefore, at this melancholly jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, apprehending themſelves in danger, and fearing a ſevere account hereafter, wanting, as they thought, Forces in <hi>England</hi> to ſtemm the Tide, which was coming in ſo furiouſly upon them; they therefore ſend Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners into <hi>Scotland,</hi> to invite the Subjects of that Nation to come in to their aſſiſtance, and rather than fail, notwithſtanding all their Proteſtations and Votes
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62943:11"/>formerly not to alter the Eſſentials of the Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, whereby they ſwore to diſſolve the Frame of the Church, as it had been by Law eſtabliſhed ever ſince the firſt excellent Reformation, notwithſtanding they knew it was not in their Power, according to the known Laws of the Kingdom, without the King's Conſent: And take it they did, and by that means procured Twenty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of their Brethren, as they called them, to invade <hi>England,</hi> againſt the King's Proclamation to the contrary, by vertue of which Act, I mean taking the Covenant, they ſhut up all the Doors againſt Peace; for, they knew at the ſame time the King was reſolved, and had often ſo declared againſt altering the Government by Biſhops, as a thing which was directly contrary to the ſatisfaction of his Conſcience, and which he could no more recede from than from his Life it ſelf. And therefore, from this, I cannot but perſwade my ſelf, they were reſolved to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the War, and engroſs all into their own hands, let what would become of the King, or thoſe Noble Perſons that took in with and adher'd to his Juſt and Righteous Cauſe.</p>
            <p>But yet, that they might pacifie the Minds of a great number of the Nation, who groaned under the Miſeries of the War, and began to ſee too much of a private Spirit under publick Pretences; they afterwards, in ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of time, conſent to a Treaty, and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge</hi> was the place pitched upon for it, to which place the King agreed, and accordingly ſent Commiſſioners, men of Honour and Honeſty, men of Fortunes and Eſtates, men of great Parts and Endowments, who underſtood the buſineſs they went about, and were very fond of healing the Nations Brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and putting things into ſuch a poſture as might ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle the King upon his juſt Rights, and the People upon their ancient Privileges, together with the addition of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62943:12"/>more ſuch as were neceſſary for that Time and Seaſon. And with what Temper they managed the whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, what Offers in the King's Name and by his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority they made, ſuch as our Anceſtors never enjoyed, nor indeed ever thought neceſſary to ask, let any man judge of, by reading the Conference it ſelf.</p>
            <p>It would ſwell this Book into too great a bulk, to run through the whole; and I ſhall therefore give the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a taſte, by which he may gueſs at all the reſt.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. As to Church-Affairs, they offered, <hi>That Freedom be left to all perſons, of what Opinion ſoever, in Matters of Ceremony; and that all the Penalties of the Law and Cuſtom which enjoin theſe Ceremonies, be ſuſpended.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>That the Biſhops ſhall exerciſe no Act of Juriſdiction or Ordination, without the Conſent and Counſel of the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, who ſhall be choſen by the Clergy of each. Dioceſs, out of the graveſt and moſt learned of the Dioceſs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>That the Biſhop keep his conſtant Reſidence in his Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, except when he ſhall be required by His Majeſty to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend him on any occaſion; and that if he be not hindered by the Infirmities of Old-Age, or Sickneſs, he preach every</hi> Sunday <hi>in ſome Church within his Dioceſs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>That the Ordination of Miniſters ſhall be alwaies in a publick and ſolemn manner, and ſtrict Rules obſerved concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Sufficiency and other Qualifications of thoſe men who ſhall be received into Holy Orders; and the Biſhop ſhall not receive any into Holy Orders without the Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation and Conſent of the Presbyters, or the major part of them.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. <hi>That competent Maintenance and Proviſions be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by Act of Parliament to ſuch Vicarages as belong to Biſhops. Deans, and Chapters, out of the Impropriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the ſeveral Pariſhes.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:62943:12"/>
               <item> 6. <hi>That no man, for the time to come, ſhall be capable of two Parſonages or Vicarages, with Cure of Souls; and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, that one or more Acts of Parliament be paſſed for regulating Viſitations, and againſt immoderate Fees in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Courts.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>And that they might be might be wanting in nothing, if any thing could ſatisfie, they declare in the cloſe, That <hi>if their Lordſhips ſhall inſiſt upon any other thing which they ſhall think neceſſary for Reformation, they were very willing to apply themſelves to the conſideration thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now let me ask any man, whether theſe men acted like the Tools and Inſtruments of a Tyrant, of one who was reſolved to ſet up his own Will in oppoſition to the Nations Good or Contentment? But yet all this was nothing, the ſtate of things is changed from what it was when they made their Proteſtation; now no Peace, no Reconciliation without the King's taking the Covenant. and thereby perjuring himſelf, and ſigning an Act for others to be perjur'd as well as himſelf, or elſe wholly to be laid aſide, as uſeleſs and unprofitable Members of the Body-Politick, and to be wholly uncapable of any Place of Truſt or Profit either in Church or State. And here I now appeal to all impartial and unprejudic'd Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, who were in fault, and who ſtood betwixt the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and a Compleat Happineſs, and what reaſon there was to continue ſuch a bloody and unnatural War. when a Peace was offered, and might have been concluded upon ſuch fair and agreeable Terms as theſe were: And they therefore that at this time cenſure and reproach the Memory of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, muſt be men ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Reſolved Prejudices, or elſe of Profound and Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid Ignorance, who never gave themſelves Leave to read his Story, and thereby to be acquainted with true Matter of Fact. The Truth is, had ſuch things been granted
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62943:13"/>as to Church-Affairs, when King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second was reſtored, I am ſure thoſe men who at this Treaty ſcornfully refuſed theſe Offers, would have <hi>thought</hi> themſelves hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in the enjoyment of them, and have bleſſed God for ſuch healing Abatements and Condeſcenſions; but God's Juſtice reckoned with many of theſe men in 62, for their Cruelty to the Epiſcopal Clergy in 43.</p>
            <p>The other great thing that came under debate at that time, was the Militia, and what Moderation the King's Commiſſioners ſhewed, and what fair Offers they made, let any man read the Conference, and then judge. In ſhort, they conſented, That the Militia, for three years, ſhould be in the Hands of Twenty Commiſſioners, the one half by the two Houſes, which certainly conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the King's Right to it, and his Anceſtors having al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies enjoyed the whole Power of diſpoſing of it, was a very great Condeſcenſion on the King's part: But, alas! it was nothing; the Inſtructions on the other ſide were to have all or none, and here they broke; and certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, any Prince, or any Noble Perſon deputed by him, as theſe were, would have broke with any Enemy, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than to have ſubmitted to ſuch ſlaviſh terms as theſe were: For, as the Commiſſioners told thoſe that appeared in the Parliaments behalf, that upon theſe Terms His Majeſty, for himſelf and his Poſterity too, would have parted with their peculiar Regal Power of being able to reſiſt their Enemies, or protect their good Subjects, and with the undoubted and never-denyed Right of the Crown, to make War and Peace.</p>
            <p>He that reads over the whole Conference, will find, it was managed on the King's Commiſſioners ſide, in all other things with the ſame Spirit, and the ſame great Abatements of the Royal Power; ſo that if there had been any real Inclination to Peace on the other ſide, a Bleſſed and Happy Peace would have enſued, and the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62943:13"/>future Miſeries and Deſolations of the War had been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented; but God did not ſee it good, neither was the Nation worthy of ſuch a Bleſſing at that time, her Sins cried aloud for further Vengeance, and ſhe had it in very great proportions.</p>
            <p>Well, after this, by the aſſiſtance of the <hi>Scots,</hi> and the new-modelling of the Army, the Parliaments Arms proſper at a great rate, and the King's Affairs conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly went backward: But however, His Majeſty, upon all promiſing Opportunities, or at leaſt, to gratifie the Tenderneſs of his Bowels towards a diſtracted and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed People, left not off to ſhew his Zeal for Peace that his poor Subjects might not live in thoſe continual Fears and Dangers they were in; and therefore he ſends from <hi>Oxford,</hi> and tells them how deeply-ſenſible he was of the Continuation of this bloody and unnatural War, and that he cannot think himſelf diſcharged of the Duty he owes to God, or the Affection and Regard he hath to the Preſervation of his People, without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant application of his earneſt Endeavours, to find ſome Expedient for the ſpeedy ending of theſe unhappy Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions. Which Meſſage, when neglected and not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, His Majeſty, Good man; ten days after, ſend another to them, extreamly wondering that they, after ſo many Expreſſions on their part, of a deep and ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſence of the Miſeries of the Afflicted Kingdom, and the Dangers incident to his Perſon during the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of this unnatural War, ſhould delay a ſafe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct to the perſons mentioned in the laſt Meſſage, who were to treat of Peace. And again, this Meſſage being ſlighted, within a few days after, he follows them with another, and tells them, Notwithſtanding the ſtrange and unexpected Delays (which can be Presidented by no former Times) to his <hi>former Meſſage,</hi> therefore he will lay aſide all Expoſtulations, as rather ſerving to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62943:14"/>time, than to contribute any Remedy to the Evils, which for the preſent do afflict this diſtracted King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: And therefore he offers to put things into ſuch a poſture, as certainly, if they had deſigned an End of the Nations Confuſions, would have terminated in an happy and ſettled Peace: But this taking no effect, he preſently, in a few days, ſends another <hi>Meſſage,</hi> with ſuch ſolemn and religious Profeſſions of his Deſire for compoſing the preſent Differences betwixt them, that truly, he that reads them, muſt upon neceſſity (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he be all Will and Prejudice) conclude, that this Great King is very wrongfully blamed, and barbarou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly uſed, when he is called by ſuch Names as very many of this Nation, out of great Good manners, and alſo proſound Reſpect to his Royal Grandchildren now happily in the Throne, think good to abuſe him withal.</p>
            <p>Now, after all this, the very month following, tho' he tells them, he needs make no Excuſe, if he ſends no more Meſſages to them, becauſe he knew very well, he ought not to do it, if he ſtood upon Puncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio's of <hi>Honour;</hi> yet nothing being equally dear to him, to the preſervation of his People, His Majeſty paſſes by many Scruples, Delays, and Neglects, and once more deſires them to give him a ſpeedy Anſwer to his laſt Meſſage, for His Majeſty believes it doth very well become him, after this very long Delay on their ſide, at laſt to utter his Impatience, ſince that the Good and Blood of his Subjects cry ſo much for Peace. Which words, how much they look like the words of a Tyrant or a Villain, as he is commonly called by our preſent pretending Patriots, I leave any man to judge.</p>
            <p>And, in the month following, in another Meſſage he ſays thus. Notwithſtanding the unexpected silence, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Anſwers, to His Majeſty's many and gracious Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62943:14"/>to both Houſe, whereby it may appear, that they deſire to attain their Ends rather by Force than Treaty, which may juſtly diſcourage His Majeſty from any more Overtures of that kind, yet His Majeſty conceives he ſhall be much wanting to his Duty to God, and in what he owes to the Safety of his People, if he ſhould not intend to prevent the Inconveniencies that may any ways hinder a ſafe and well-grounded Peace. Which words certainly are not the words of a Tyrant.</p>
            <p>Well, after theſe <hi>Meſſages</hi> from <hi>Oxford,</hi> His Majeſty, for Reaſons beſt known to himſelf, leaving <hi>Oxford</hi> in a diſguiſe, and committing himſelf to the <hi>Scotch</hi> Army then by <hi>Newark;</hi> pray let us ſee what he does when in his Enemies Hands: Why, Good man, ſtill he breathes nothing but Peace, as you may ſee by the following ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; for, from <hi>Southwell</hi> he writes to the two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and tells them, That he withdrew from <hi>Oxford</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſecure his own Perſon, and with no intention to continue the War any longer, nor to make any Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on between his two Kingdoms, but to give ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment to them both, as, by the Bleſſing of God, he might ſee an happy and well-grounded Peace, thereby to bring Proſperity to theſe Kingdoms anſwerable to the beſt time of his Progenitors: And, that he might ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie them he was in good-earneſt, and deſigned no Tricks by way of Poſtſcript he tells them, That being da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to ſhun the further Effuſion of Blood, and to evidence his Real Intentions to Peace, he is willing that his Forces in and about <hi>Oxford</hi> be disbanded, and the Fortifications of the City diſmantled, they receiving Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Conditions, which being granted to the Town and Forces, His Majeſty will give the like. Order to the reſt of the Garriſons. And, pray let the honeſt Reader judge where lay the fault now, and who rid the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and prolonged its Miſeries, the King, or thoſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:62943:15"/>whom our preſent Pretenders to the only Loyalty to Their preſent Majeſties, call <hi>The Old Blades, The Brave Fellows, The noble Defenders of their Laws and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try;</hi> though at the ſame time they trampled them all under their Feet, and ſet up their own Wills in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition even to <hi>Magna Charta</hi> if ſelf. And ſurely, he that hath but half an Eye, may ſee who were the Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuers of the War, and for what reaſon, namely, <hi>To ride upon the high places of the Earth, to kill and take poſſeſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And after this the Great and Good man ſends a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the City of <hi>London,</hi> in which he tells them, That nothing is more grievous to him, than the Troubles and Diſtractions of his People; and nothing on Earth is more deſired by him, than that it Religion and Peace, with all the comfortable Fruits of both, they may hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth live under him in all Godlineſs and Honeſty: And this Profeſſion, ſays he to the City, we make for no other end, but that they may immediately know from himſelf, his Integrity and full Reſolution to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with his Parliament in every thing for the ſettling of Truth and Peace. Words becoming the Excellent and Religious Temper of this Great man.</p>
            <p>After this, he ſends another <hi>Meſſage</hi> from <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> to the two Houſes, in which, among many other things, he deſires them, That the Propoſitions of Peace ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten promiſed and ſo much expected, may be ſpeedily ſent to him, that upon conſideration of them, he may apply himſelf to give ſuch ſatisfaction as may be the found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of a firm Peace. And, to convince every man who would be convinc'd, that he was in all his Deſires for Peace the very ſame man, that is, True, and in Earneſt, the ſame day he writes this Letter to the Houſes, he ſends another to the Governours of his remaining Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons, telling them, That having reſolved to comply
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62943:15"/>with the Deſires of his Parliament, in every thing which might be for the Good of his Subjects, and leave no means uneſſay'd for removing all Differences between them; therefore he had thought ſit, the more to evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence the Reality of his Intentions of ſettling <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> happy and firm Peace, to require them, upon honourable <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, to quit thoſe Towns, Forts, and Caſtles i<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ed to them by him, and to disband all the Forces under their ſeveral Commands. And, pray what Tyranny is there in all this? And, upon what account is this Great man ſo baſely accuſed as he is at this time by Thouſands of this Nation? Certainly, when they read all this, they muſt needs fall foul upon themſelves, for being guilty of ſo much Unworthineſs and Diſhoneſty, to the Memory of ſo great and good a man as he was.</p>
            <p>But now ſome may ſay, You talk all for the King here Pray what ſaid the two Houſes to all theſe <hi>Meſſages</hi>? Were they wholly deaf to his Offers? Did they <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>orn any Anſwer to his Propoſals? No, no; that they might ſeem to be for Peace, they ſent Propoſitions to the King at <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> but, I muſt tell the Reader, they were ſuch as would make any man, that wiſhes well to his Native Kingdom, ſick to read them; ſuch Demands, as no man that had any ſenſe of Honour could poſſibly grant. For firſt, he muſt juſtifie by an Act of State all that they had unjuſtly done to him; he muſt be obliged to take the Covenant, and ſign an Act for others to do ſo too; he muſt part with the Power of the Sword, and indeed, be thereby but a meer Cypher in the Kingdom; and that which muſt needs grate upon a generous and noble Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ſuch as his was, he muſt paſs an Act to except from Pardon, and to lay at theſe mens mercileſs Feet the beſt and trueſt Friends he had in his Kingdom, ſuch as from Principles of Honour and Duty had ventured both their Lives and their great Eſtates in his Service. And, Good
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62943:16"/>man, becauſe he would not ſign all theſe, together with many other unreaſonable things, he muſt forſooth be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>then,</hi> and <hi>now alſo,</hi> a Tyrant.</p>
            <p>It would be too tedious to entertain the Reader with what His Majeſty made by way of Anſwer to theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, and beſides, ſwell this Paper beyond its deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed bulk, therefore I do refe<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r the Reader to the Royal Papers themſelves, only thus much I muſt tell the World; That His Majeſty thought nothing, at this time, would ſo ſoon conduce to a Peace as a Perſonal Treaty, which therefore he preſſed hard for, not doubting but by that means they might come on both ſides to a true under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of one another; and therefore, that he might not fail of having this Requeſt granted him, he ends his Letter to them with theſe words. <hi>To conclude, 'tis your King who deſires to be heard (the which if refuſed by a King to a Subject, he would be thought a Tyrant for it) and for that end which all Men profeſs to deſire; wherefore His Majeſty conjures you, as you deſire to ſhew your ſelves really what you profeſs, even as you are good Chriſtians and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, that you will accept this his Offer, which he is confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent God will ſo bleſs, that it will be the readieſt means by which theſe Kingdoms again may become a Comfort to their Friends, and a Terrour to their Enemies.</hi> Which words are not the words of a Monſter or a Man of Blood, as ſome vile men are now ready to call him, (the greater is their ſhame) but the words of a truly-compaſſionate Father of his Country, whoſe Heart bled for the Wounds of his Children and the Miſeries of the Nation.</p>
            <p>After all this, the <hi>Scots,</hi> notwithſtanding all their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and Obligations, ſell him to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Parliament, and His Majeſty is put into the Hands of Commiſſioners appointed to keep and watch his Perſon, and brought by them to <hi>Holdenby-Houſe</hi> in <hi>Northamptonſhire,</hi> where his Converſation was ſo agreeable and ſweet, his daily Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62943:16"/>ſo ſtrong and convincing, that he changed: the Opinion of many that were about him, ſo that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came conſtant Admirers of his Virtues ever after, and great Bewailers of having had an Hand in bringing him into thoſe Streights, out of which they could not now extricate him.</p>
            <p>Now, while he was here, let us ſee what further Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers he made for Peace. The firſt Meſſage to both Houſes from this place, acquaints us with his bad Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; that his Servants were denied acceſs to him, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it were a very few, whom they appointed themſelves; and that it was a declared Crime for any but the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, or ſuch as were particularly permitted by them, to converſe with His Majeſty; or that any Letters ſhould be given to, or received from him (a condition no man, much leſs a Prince, could be proud of.) Yet he tells them, and therefore would not ſtand upon that, That he preferred a Right Underſtanding betwixt him and his Parliaments of both Kingdoms, which might make a firm and laſting Peace in all his Dominions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any Particular of his own, or any earthly Bleſſing: And, to ſhew he was in earneſt, he then makes ſuch Conceſſions to them, as certainly would have been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of by any ſort of men, but ſuch as had not yet ſatisfied their own Avarice, Ambition, and other Luſts, and therefore were reſolved to perpetuate the Diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Kingdom, in order to continue themſelves in Places of Wealth and Power: For, he offered to ſettle their Church-Government for Three Years, and at the ſame time, the Aſſembly of Divines at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> and the <hi>Directory,</hi> provided His Majeſty and his Houſhold were not hindered from the Form of God's Service which they formerly had. Further, he offers another Act for the better obſervation of the Lord's Day: He conſents, that the whole Power of the Militia, both by Sea and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62943:17"/>Land, for the ſpace of Ten Years, be in the Hands of ſuch Perſons as the two Houſes ſhould nominate, giving them a full Power, during the ſaid ſpace, to change or elſe to continue the ſaid Perſons in their ſeveral Offices: Which when he had offered, he conjures his two Houſes of Parliament, as they are <hi>Engliſh-men,</hi> and Lovers of Peace, by the Duty they owe to His Majeſty their King, and by the Bowels of Compaſſion they have to their fellow-Subjects, that they will accept of this His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty's Offer, whereby the Joyful News of Peace may be reſtored to this languiſhing Kingdom. Which Offers had ſo great an eftect upon the Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> (tho' they had none at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi>) that they forthwith pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioned the Lord Mayor and Common-Council, and tell them thereby, That taking into ſerious conſideration, how Religion, His Majeſty's Honour and Safety, the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges of parliament, and Liberty of the Subject, were at preſent greatly endangered, and like to be deſtroyed; and alſo ſadly weighing with themſelves what means might likely prove moſt effectual to procure a firm and laſting Peace, without the further effuſion of Chriſtian <hi>Engliſh</hi> Blood, have therefore enter'd into a ſolem En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, and do humbly and earneſtly deſire, that the whole City may joyn together by all lawfull and poſſible means, as one man, in hearty Endeavours for His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's preſent coming up to his two Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with Honour, Safery, and Freedom, and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the nearer approaches of the Army, there to confirm ſuch things as he hath granted in his laſt Meſſage, in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the Propoſitions of both Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>Which Petition, you muſt underſtand, was not preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by them called the <hi>Cavalier Party,</hi> but by ſuch as had ventured their <hi>Money</hi> and <hi>Plate</hi> for the Cauſe, and had taken the Covenant, and many of them expoſed their Perſons to fight for that which they through miſtake,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62943:17"/>apprehended Religions and the Nations Cauſe, yet theſe men were ſo far from thinking His Majeſty ſuch a Bad man, as ſome deſigning men now report him to be, that they looked upon his Conceſſions, as every ways anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that for which at firſt they took up Arms.</p>
            <p>Well, after this, the King, upon more than ordinary grounds to believe that his Perſon was in danger at <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pton-Court,</hi> (whither the Army, after they took him by force from <hi>Holdenby,</hi> after many removes, had carried him) makes an eſcape from them by night, but withal, leaves a Paper behind him upon the Table, wherein he gives an account with what patience he had endured a redious reſtraint, which, ſo long as he had any hopes, that this ſort of Suffering might conduce to the Peace of his Kingdom, or the hindrance of more effuſion of Blood, he did willingly undergo; but finding by too-certain Proofs, that this his continued Patience would not only turn to his perſonal Ruine, but likewiſe be of much more Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice than Furtherance to the Publick Good, he thought he was bound, as well by natural as political Obligations, to ſeek his Safety, by retiring himſelf for ſome time from the publick view both of Friends and Enemies. And after he had appealed to all indifferent men, to judge, whether he had not juſt cauſe to free himſelf from the hands of thoſe who changed their Principles with their Conditions, and who were not aſhamed openly to intend the Deſtruction of the Nobility, and who had changed and put ſtrict Guards upon him, with the diſcharging moſt of all thoſe Servants of his, whom formerly they willingly admitted to wait upon him: After he had ſaid all this, with a great deal more <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s the Reaſons of that Retirement, he concludes the P<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> with theſe words: <hi>Let me be but heard with Freedom, Honour, and Safety, and I ſhall inſtantly break through this Cloud of Retirement, and ſhew my ſelf really to be</hi> Pater Patriae. And here I cannot forbear again to ask,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62943:18"/>What Tyranny is there in all this? and, With what Face is this Great man reflected upon ſo barbarouſly at this day, as he is by ſome men in all parts of the Kingdom (an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of thing, conſidering that thoſe that ſprung from his Loins are in the Throne)? Certainly they either never read his Story, or if they did, they are reſolved againſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, and keep alive in their Breaſts ſuch Reſentments, on purpoſe to help them to ſerve another turn when op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity (which God forbid) ſhall offer of the ſame nature.</p>
            <p>The next News, after this, we hear of His Majeſty, is from the <hi>Iſle of Wright,</hi> under the Command of <hi>Hammond</hi> the Governor, into whoſe hands he had committed himſelf.</p>
            <p>And, pray let us ſee how he carries himſelf there, and whether he did not make all Eſſays for Peace, and the Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement of the Nation upon a firm and laſting bottom, that ſo King and People might enjoy what belongs to them both, without future fear or danger. Yes, yes; we find him again at the ſame Work, labouring with all his Might for Peace: For, tho' he left <hi>Hampton Court</hi> but the 11th of <hi>Nov.</hi> 47, yet on the 17th. he ſends Propoſitions for Peace, wherein he grants again what he had done before ſo great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Contentment and Satisfaction of the Citizens of <hi>London;</hi> but alas, it ſeems to be too late now, for he had loſt his Power, and the Faction reſolved never to part with it again, they had taſted the ſweetneſs of Uſurpation, and the reliſh would not caſily go out of their Mouths; and therefore, as he ſell low in his Offers, ſo they roſe higher, and made bigger Demands, and to ſhew their great De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of Peace, or indeed, which hath more Truth in it, of continuing themſelves in Places of Truſt and Honour, which they thought they could not do without making the Breach betwixt the King and themſelves wider and wider; therefore the more crafty and ſubtile Party of the Houſe of Commons (which were the <hi>Independent Party,</hi> who had got at that time too great a ſway both in the Houſe and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62943:18"/>Army) procure four Bills and Propoſitions to be ſent to the King to ſign, ready drawn up, together with the Heads of 23 more, which whoſoever will be pleaſed to read, may eaſily judge of the Spirit that then reigned, and the wicked and deſtructive Deſigns then on foot: Bills, that they were aſſured beforehand, if the moſt ſolemn Proteſtations on the King's ſide could convince them, he would never paſs, and indeed, which upon bare Principles of Conſcience he could never paſs, without an utter overthrow of the Peace and Satisfaction of his Mind. And ſo cunning were they to make Demands at this time that might have no effect, that the Bills they ſent (which they could not but fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee) the <hi>Scots</hi> Commiſſioners proteſted againſt to the King, and therefore they propoſed ahem ſo high, that the King might <hi>deny</hi> them, and the War be thereby prolon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</p>
            <p>The Anſwer His Majeſty makes to theſe four Bills, is great and admirable, to tranſcribe the whole would be too tedious; in ſhort, he tells them, That he believes it clear to all Underſtandings, that theſe Bills contain (as they are now penned) not only the diveſting himſelf of all Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty, and that without a poſſibility of recovering it ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to himſelf or Succeſſors, (except by repeal of thoſe Bills) but alſo the making his Conceſſions guilty of the greateſt Preſſures that can be laid upon the Subject, as in other particulars, ſo, by giving an Arbitrary and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limitted Power to the two Houſes for ever, and after much more ſaid upon that Subject, he concludes his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer thus: That <hi>His Majeſty is very much at eaſe within himſelf for having fulfilled the Offices both of a Chriſtian and a King, and will patiently wait the good Pleaſure of Almighty God, to incline the Hearts of his two Houſes to conſider their King, and to compaſſionate their fellow-Subject's Miſeries.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:62943:19"/>
            <p> Which Anſwer, and Refuſal of his to ſign theſe four Bills, ſo cauſeleſly enſlam'd the then Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, that, as if they were ſole Maſters in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> they vote, That they will make no further Addreſſes or Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications to the King, nor that any Addreſs be made to him by any other perſons, without the Leave of both Houſes: And, to ſhew their Abſolute and Uncontroula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Power, they vote, That whoever ſhall make Breach of this Order, ſhall incurr the Penaties of High Treaſon. Nay, to pin the Basket up, they vote, They will alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive no more Meſſages from the King, and enjoyn all perſons to receive and bring none from him. Here is your Loyalty indeed! This is to act as becomes humble and dutiful Subjects with a witneſs; what pity it is, that theſe great <hi>Heroes</hi> Statues are not ſet up in every Corner of the Kingdom, with this Label at their Mouths, <hi>No more Addreſſes to our King.</hi> But, What ſays the Good man to all this? What Reſentments hath he up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this great Honour done to him, thus to be as it were dethron'd, by thoſe who were under the Obligation of Oaths of Fidelity to him and his Poſterity? Good man, he preſently makes a Declaration in Anſwer to theſe Votes, and begins, <hi>Am I thus laid aſide, and muſt I not ſpeak for my ſelf? No, I will ſpeak, and that to all my People;</hi> and ſo goes on with Reflections upon his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, enough to melt the Hearts of any but thoſe who made thoſe hard-hearted Votes; or thoſe of the ſame Principles. Now I am under a Neceſſity of of Brevity, or elſe I would tranſcribe the whole, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, I am ſure, I ſhould force Tears from all tender per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Eyes; I referr therefore the Reader to the Papers themſelves, only tell him he concludes it thus: <hi>It may be eaſily gathered, how theſe Men intend to govern who have uſed me thus: And if it be my Hard Fate to fall, together with the Liberty of this Kingdom, I ſhall not bluſh for my
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:62943:19"/>ſelf, but much lament the future Miſeries of my People, the which I ſhall ſtill pray God to avert, whatever becomes of me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this, how theſe Votes were recalled, and a freſh Treaty agreed upon in the <hi>Iſle of Wight;</hi> how the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was managed; what Strength of Reaſon and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the King manifeſted, both in his Debates about Church as well as State-Affairs, any man may ſatisfie himſelf that reads the Accounts from <hi>Auguſt</hi> to <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> in the year 48, where he will find at laſt His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, for Peace, ſake, makes ſuch Conceſſions, that the major part of the Houſe, after many hours debate, came to this Vote; That His Majeſty's Conceſſions to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of Parliament upon the Treaty, are ſufficient Grounds for ſettling the Peace of the Kingdom. And happy had it been for the whole Nation, if they had paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſuch a Vote ſome years before, upon what the King offered them, they had prevented the waſting of abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Blood and Treaſure; but alas, their Eyes were in their Heads now too late, the Army was now too much poyſoned with Common-wealth and deſtructive Principles, and therefore, notwithſtanding all their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Aſſurances of Submiſſion and Faithfulneſs to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, they make bold to let them know, they have been under the Juriſdiction of better Maſters, and have learned another Leſſon, and therefore, when the Houſe met again, they very fairly lay violent hands upon their Perſons, and forcibly pluck them from their Duty, and confine a great part of them, keeping them under a ſtrict Guard. What follow'd after this, is known to all the World: The Great, the Good, the Wiſe, the Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending King, his Perſon is ſeiz'd by order of the Army, he is brought up to <hi>London,</hi> try'd and condemn'd by a Mock-Court of Juſtice, againſt all Law, Juſtice, Honour,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:62943:20"/>Oaths, and Promiſes; and, at laſt, barbarouſly murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by his own Palace.</p>
            <p>And thus died <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, the Glory of the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Monarchs, the Mirror of Patience, the great Pattern of Religion and Devotion, and whoſe Name among good and unprejudic'd men hath ever ſince bloſſom'd in the Duſt; and may the Judgments that have followed the Nation ſince, be the laſt upon the account of that horrid and unheard-of Murther. <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have reſerved an Anſwer to ſome particular Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which are commonly made by this Great Man's Enemies againſt him, by way of Poſtſcript, having not had a fair occaſion to bring it into the Body of this little Book; only before I make it, I muſt beg leave to tell thee what I have obſerved concerning the men that are now ſo buſie in defaming and ſcandalizing this Great and Pious Prince, namely, That they are moſt of them perſons that were not born when the Horrid Murther of the King was committed, and that have not read his Story at all, but are only put on by old Foxes, that loſt, by the Reſtauration of <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, what they never had a legal Right to, and therefore long to be dabbling again in Crown and Church-Lands; which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is the true Notion of theſe mens Liberties and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of the Subject.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:62943:20"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> They conſidently ſay, That he was a <hi>Papiſh,</hi> or at leaſt, Popiſhly inclined; and therefore, by way of Scorn, nothing is more uſual, than to hear them ſaying, That the late King <hi>James</hi> was the beſt of the Three; meaning King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, and his two Sons that reigned after him.</p>
            <p>Now, by way of Anſwer to this baſe and falſe Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, I will not trouble thee, Reader, with any tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and long Defence, for they that hear this Scandal, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they have looked into the Life and Converſation of this Great man, muſt both ſcorn and pity the Malice as well as Ignorance of ſuch as lay ſuch an Aſperſion at his Door: And for an eternal confutation of it, I beg of thee to take good notice of this true Story.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty being to receive the Sacrament, in 1643, at <hi>Christ-Church</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> from the Hands of the Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Ardmagh,</hi> riſing up from his Knees, and beckoning to the Archbiſhop ſaid,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Lord, I eſpy here many reſolved Proteſtants, who may delare to the World the Reſolution I now make.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I have, to the utmoſt of my power, prepared my Soul to become a worthy Receiver; and may I ſo receive Comfort by the Bleſſed Sacrament, as I do intend the Eſtabliſhment of the True-reformed Protestant Religion, as it stood in its Beauty in the happy Days of Queen</hi> Elizabeth, <hi>without any Connivance at Popery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I bleſs God, that in the midst of theſe publick Distra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, I have still liberty to communicate. And may this Sacrament be my Damnation, if my Heart do not joyn with my Lips in this Protestation.</hi> And he that will continue to ſcandalize this Great Perſon, after he has read this Story, upon this account, is reſolved to be an incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable —</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:62943:21"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Another thing they lay to his charge at this time, is, That he ſet on foot and encouraged the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebellion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> They that talk at this rate, I am ſure, have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver read his Story; or if they have, it has been with an invincible and reſolved Prejudice. His frequent and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Deteſtations of it, his groaning under the Miſeries and Murders of his poor Proteſtant Subjects there, his offering to go in Perſon to ſubdue the Rebels, are ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Vindications of him, againſt this vile Defamation, and will ever be received as ſuch amongſt good men.</p>
            <p>But, to ſtrike this Objection dead, over and above all thoſe Defences the King made for himſelf, and the Scorn and Defiance he gave to the pretended Broad Seal to countenance the Rebellion, which is Forgery all over, give me leave to lay before the Reader theſe two things.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Macquire,</hi> a great and bloody Rebel, being taken Priſoner, and conveyed to <hi>London,</hi> and there try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for his Life at the <hi>King's-Bench-Bar,</hi> for High Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, where being found guilty, he had Sentence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd againſt him, as a Traytor, which Sentence was particularly executed in the preſence of the Sheriff and, it's believ'd, of Fifteen thouſand Spectators.</p>
            <p>Now, when he came to Execution, the Sheriff abjur'd him by the dreadful Tribunal of God, before which ſhortly he was to appear, and for the clearing and eaſing of his Conſcience, that he would then ingenuouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs whom he knew guilty of the ſame Crime, namely, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebellion; upon which the Criminal, though the Rope was about his Neck, and he half way up the Ladder, yet, by Name, he acquitted King <hi>Charles</hi> from being any ways privy to it: Nay, ſays my Author, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing caſt off the Ladder, and when he had tryed what Hanging in part was, being reprieved, and had no ſmall
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:62943:21"/>hopes given him of a Pardon, he ſtill perſiſted in the ſame Proteſtation. And that which further convinces me, and ſo it will any unprejudic'd man beſides, of the truth of this, is, That when they came to draw up the Charge againſt him, in order to his Trial and Condemnation, though their buſineſs was to blacken him with all the foul Imputations their Malice could rake up, and they did ſo, yet not one word in the whole touching his abetting or countenancing the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebellion; which certainly they neither could nor would have omitted, if they had had any Grounds to believe and to charge him with it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The laſt Objection againſt him is, his Divine and Holy Book: It is not to be imagined with what Induſtry they have, within this laſt year, endeavoured to perſwade the World it was a Forgery, and not of his compiling; and there is a certain <hi>Eſſex</hi> Doctor of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, who has aſſiſted this Objection to the utmoſt of his power, with a falſe Story, which I will preſently refute, and ſet the whole in a true and proper Light.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I could never obtain Leave of my ſelf to believe that any Man could write at that divinerate, but he that felt the Miſeries that ſuggeſt ſuch Thoughts and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Meditations; the various Conditions of men, good men, wonderfully help them, in their Retirements and Solitudes, to Divine Intercourſes and Aſpirations; and he that could counterfeit ſuch things, and make ſuch Appeals to God, without being in ſuch Conditions as thoſe Appeals ſuppoſe, muſt be rather next to an Atheiſt than a good Chriſtian. And if the <hi>Eſſex</hi> Doctor had any value for the Memory of his deceaſed Friend, he would certainly have forborn telling it in all places, with a more than uſual Confidence, as he hath done, and that for this one reaſon.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:62943:22"/>
            <p> The Story, in ſhort, that he tells, is this; That Dr. <hi>Gauden,</hi> then of <hi>Bocking</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> made this Book, and ſent him; then his Curate, to the Preſs with it, which command he obey'd, and accordingly did ſo carry it, in order to its printing.</p>
            <p>Now the Truth of the Story is thus: There was one Mr. <hi>Simmons,</hi> a learned and pious Miniſter, who lived near Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and who, out of a true Affection to His then Majeſty's Perſon and Cauſe, writ a learned Defence of the King, with which the King was ſo pleaſed, that he preſently reſolved, that this perſon ſhould have the peruſal and correction of his Book, and accordingly ſends it by a truſty Meſſenger.</p>
            <p>The Book, when looked over by him, did ſo affect him, (and no wonder) that he could not forbear ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for his Neighbour <hi>Gauden,</hi> in order to make him happy with himſelf, in the ſight and reading of ſuch an ineſtimable Jewel; Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> would not be denied the kindneſs of taking the Book home with him, for a few days, which upon importunity Mr. <hi>Simmonds</hi> (knowing the Dr. a Well-wiſher at that time to the King) granted; Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> preſently falls to tranſcribing of it, and in ſome days, with great Labour and Application, finiſhes it, and ſo returns the Original to Mr. <hi>Simmonds</hi> again.</p>
            <p>Within a while the great Storm coming upon the King, which at laſt, God knows, wholly overſet him, Dr. <hi>Gauden,</hi> out of a true Affection to his Maſter the King, hoping thereby to do him Service, ſends his Copy by the Hands of this Doctor to the Preſs: And ſo far, and no farther was he concerned in it.</p>
            <p>And whereas it is ſaid, that Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> told King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second he made the Book, the Truth of the Story is this: That he putting in for the Biſhoprick of <hi>Worcester,</hi> and meeting with ſome oppoſition from Biſhop <hi>Sheldon,</hi> the King asked him what Pretences he
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:62943:22"/>had to ſo great a Favour; he anſwered, That he put out his Fathers Book; which Anſwer, tho' true in ſome ſence, yet being ambiguouſly ſpoken, as it got him the Biſhoprick, ſo it alſo gave Riſe to the late Earl of <hi>Angleſey</hi>'s <hi>Memorandum,</hi> which hath made ſo great noiſe in the World.</p>
            <p>But, to put all things out of doubt concerning this Book, give me leave to tell this Story: I was, not many weaks ago, in Converſation with Sir <hi>John Brattle</hi> a worthy perſon, and who hath long enjoy'd a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Office in the Royal Mint, with whom diſcourſing about King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, and particularly of the Suſpicions raiſed of the Truth of the Book, he frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly told me, and aſſured me the Truth of this Story.</p>
            <p>That in the year 47. King <hi>Charles</hi> having drawn up the moſt conſiderable part of this Book, and having writ it in ſome looſe Papers, at different times, deſired Biſhop <hi>Juxon</hi> to get ſome Friend of his (whom he could commend to him as a truſty perſon) to look it over, and to put it into an exact method; the Biſhop pitched upon Sir <hi>John</hi>'s Father, whom he had been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted withal for many years, who undertaking the Task, was aſſiſted by this his Son, who declares, he ſate up with his Father ſome nights, to aſſiſt him in metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizing theſe Papers, all writ with the King's own Hand: Thanks be to God, Sir <hi>John</hi> is yet alive, and is ready to give the ſame Account to any man that asks him.</p>
            <p>And whoſoever, after this, will ſuſpect this Book, is certainly a man of that temper, who will keep up his Prejudices againſt this Great man, in ſpight of all Evidences, though as clear as the Sun at Noon:
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:62943:23"/>And for my own part, I muſt tell him, that I think it not worth the while, to attempt his further ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction; becauſe <hi>nullum remedium Deus poſuit contuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae,</hi> God Almighty hath not provided a Remedy for Reſolved Stubbornneſs in the ordinary courſe of dealing with Men; and if nothing but Miracles will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince them, I have no Commiſſion to pretend to them.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
